Warren Mitofsky Papers 2008.0071
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Warren Mitofsky Papers
undated, 1893-2006
2008.0071
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
33.7 Linear feet
The Warren Mitofsky Papers span the years 1948 through 2006. A large majority of the papers concern Mitofksy’s involvement with the major news networks in various primaries and elections in American and foreign elections during this period, including his conducting of exit polls, which he invented in 1967.
Mitofsky, Warren J.
Arrangement
The collection is comprised of twelve series. Series 1: Elections, Series 2: Public Opinion and Data Gathering, Series 3: Election Projections, Series 4: Litigation, Series 5: Legislative Materials, Series 6: Surveys and Studies, Series 7: Political Articles and Papers, Series 8: Company and Organization Materials, Series 9: Personal, Series 10: Magazines and Journals, Series 11: Multimedia, and Series 12: Newspapers and Oversize.
Scope and Content
The Warren Mitofsky Papers span the years 1948 through 2006. A large majority of the papers concern Mitofksy’s involvement with the major news networks in various primaries and elections in American and foreign elections during this period, including his conducting of exit polls, which he invented in 1967. The collection includes polls, memoranda, correspondence, television transcripts, and election projection models of the major news organizations and polling groups such as ABC, NBC, CBS, Voter Research and Surveys (VRS), Voter News Service (VNS), and Mitofsky International. Many administrative papers, such as internal memoranda, meeting minutes, handbooks, manuals, and company proposals are found for these companies as well. Another portion of this collection is comprised of articles and papers on the practice and methodology of polling and the various fields involved with it. In particular, multiple sections involve the controversy of exit polls in affecting elections, with a majority concentrating on the elections of 1984-1985. Materials within this subject include legislative reports, testimony before House and Senate hearings, and journal and newspaper articles. The Papers also contain of legal briefs of cases in which he was involved, as well as associated affidavits and witness testimony. Many articles written by Mitofsky, as well as correspondence with others in the field of polling and politics, can found within his personal papers.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to to public polling and survey research. See especially the Papers of James Vicary, Samuel Lubell, Daniel Yankelovich, Paul K. Perry and Archibald Crossley. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Provenance and Acquisition
The collection was donated by Mr. Mitofsky's family in 2008.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Biography
Warren Mitofsky, American political pollster, was born on September 17, 1934, in the Bronx, NY. He attended and graduated from Guilford College in Greensboro, NC, and did graduate work at the University of North Carolina. At the University of Minnesota he became a doctoral candidate in mass communications but did not complete his degree. After ending his graduate studies, Mitofsky began working for the U.S. Census Bureau. While there, he designed many surveys on demographics including those for the poverty program and presidential commissions. Also during this time of employment, he developed, along with his colleague Joseph Waksberg, an efficient random digit dialing sampling method that would be widely implemented and an industry standard for many years. Mitofsky left the Census Bureau for CBS News in 1967 to become the executive director of the election and survey unit, a post he held until 1990. Inspired by George Fine’s surveys of moviegoers after they left the theater, he conducted and invented the first exit poll in the 1967 Kentucky Gubernatorial Election. At the same time he developed the analysis and projection systems used to call elections. Exit polls were first used in national elections in 1972 and remain in use to the present day. In 1975, Mitofsky started the CBS News/ New York Times poll and directed it for the next fifteen years. During this time he developed and implemented many improvements to the system of exit poll sampling and statistical methods. In 1989 he proposed an independent exit poll organization to provide exit polls for the television networks. The news networks rejected this idea wanting to retain more control over the polls. In 1990, he instead started and became the director of Voter Research & Surveys ( VRS). VRS was a consortium of the major of the four major television news networks of ABC, CBS, CNN and NBC who would pool their resources to conduct exit polling and predict election results. In 1994 they merged with News Election Service ( NES) to become Voter News Service ( VNS). In 1993, Warren left VRS to create his own independent company, Mitofsky International. This new organization handled exit polls not only in the U.S. but around the world, including Mexico, Russia and the Philippines. Mitofsky’s vision of an independent polling company handling exit polling came to fruition in the 2003 California Gubernatorial Recall. In this and subsequent elections, Mitofsky International partnered with Edison Media Research to conduct exit polls for ABC, CBS, CNN, Fox, NBC, and The Associated Press while maintaining complete authority over technical decisions. Mitofsky was also very involved with polling outside the news industry. He was president of the American Association for Public Opinion Research ( AAPOR), the National Council on Public Polls ( NCPP), and the Research Industry Coalition (RIC). In 1995, he was a fellow at Harvard's Kennedy School of Government and in the same year he was the Howard R. Marsh Visiting Professor at the University of Michigan. In 1999, AAPOR gave him their lifetime achievement award, hailing ''his continuing concern for survey quality.'' He was also a Fellow of the American Statistical Association and served on the board of the Roper Center and the NY State Committee on Open Government. Warren Mitofsky died September 1, 2006.
Mitofsky, Warren J.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Correspondence.; Memoranda.; Public opinion polls--United States.; Public opinion polls.; Public opinion--United States.; Public polling collections
- Series I: Elections, 1948-2006
  - Subseries A: U. S. Presidential Elections, 1948-2004
    - 1948
      - ABC Political Coverage (Box 1)
      - CBS Political Coverage (Box 1)
      - NBC Political Coverage (Box 1)
      - Clippings (Box 1)
    - 1952
      - CBS Political Coverage (Box 1)
      - NBC Political Coverage (Box 1)
      - Clippings (Box 1)
    - 1956
      - ABC Political Coverage (Box 1)
      - CBS Political Coverage (Box 1)
      - Clippings (Box 1)
    - 1960
      - ABC Political Coverage (Box 1)
      - Interviews made among non-voters concerning election debates (Box 1)
      - CBS News Reports (Box 1)
      - Election Study III: Concerning issues and candidates by Elmo Roper and Associates (Box 1)
      - NBC Political Coverage (Box 1)
    - 1964
      - ABC Political Coverage (Box 1)
      - Brief Report on the Wisconsin Republican Primary, 1964 January (Box 1)
      - CBS News Correspondent's notebook, New Hampshire Primary (Box 1)
      - CBS News Reports (Box 1)
      - CBS Political Coverage (Box 1)
      - Election clippings (Box 1)
      - Election ephemera (Box 1)
      - NBC Political Coverage: January - May (Box 1)
      - NBC Political Coverage: June - November (Box 1)
      - Survey of the New Hampshire Republican primary for President, January 30 (Box 1)
      - Vote Profile Analysis (Box 1)
      - Voter Profile Anaylsis results (Box 1)
    - 1968
      - ABC Network Election System (Box 1)
      - ABC Political Coverage (Box 1)
      - CBS Political Coverage Plans, Parts I-2 (Box 1)
      - Detailed Analysis of Issues & Forces in the 1968 Presidential Election (Box 1)
      - Election Night Calls (Box 1)
      - Election Night Post-Mortem (Box 1)
      - Instructions for Data Collection (Box 1)
      - NBC Political Coverage (Box 1)
      - NES Political Coverage (Box 1)
      - Outliers (Box 1)
      - Political Articles (Box 1)
      - Pre-election Analysis (Box 1)
      - Primaries, Part 1-2 (Box 1)
      - Voting Prediction Model: Kennedy & McCarthy in Indiana (Box 1)
      - Vote Profile Analysis (Box 1)
      - Vote Profile Analysis Design and Results, Part 1 (Box 2)
      - Vote Profile Analysis Design and Results, Part 2 (Box 2)
      - Vote Profile Analysis Design and Results for Primaries (Box 2)
    - 1972
      - CBS Election Day Survey (Box 2)
      - CBS Election Night (Box 2)
      - Characteristics of New Voters (Box 2)
      - Correspondence Regarding Polling Restrictions (Box 2)
      - Election Articles (Box 2)
      - Election Data (Box 2)
      - Election Day Survey (Box 2)
      - Perils of Polling (Box 2)
      - Pre-Election Analysis (Box 2)
      - Voting and Registration in the Election of November 1972 (Box 2)
      - Voter Profile Analysis, Computations, and Post-Mortem (Box 2)
    - 1976
      - Campaign ’76: A Reference to Official Vote Returns (Box 2)
      - CBS Mathematical Models (Box 2)
      - CBS Political Coverage (Box 2)
      - Election articles (Box 2)
      - New Hampshire Primary (Box 2)
      - Presidential Election Materials (Box 2)
      - Qualitative Analysis of the Non-Voter Attitudes (Box 2)
      - •••• Random Telephone Numbers (Box 2)
      - Republican National Convention (Box 2)
      - Registration and Voting in November 1976 – Jurisdictions Covered by the Voting Rights Act Amendment (Box 2)
      - Turnout (Box 2)
      - Voting and Registration in the Election of November 1976 (Box 2)
      - Voter Profile Analysis (Box 2)
    - 1980
      - Carter in the Polls (Box 2)
      - CBS Campaign ’80: Exit Poll (Box 2)
      - CBS Election Coverage (Box 3)
      - CBS National Survey (Box 2)
      - CBS News/ New York Times Polls – Correspondence (Box 2)
      - CBS News/ New York Times Post Election Study (Box 2)
      - Decision ’80: General Election Poll Results (Box 2)
      - Election Results, Calls, etc. (Box 2)
      - Los Angeles Times Post Election Poll (Box 2)
      - Maine Caucus (Box 2)
      - National Election Call Reports (Box 2)
      - New Hampshire Primary (Box 2)
      - New York Times Political Poll Articles (Box 2)
      - Post 1980 Review Memos (Box 2)
      - Pre-Election polls (2 folders) (Box 2)
      - Pre-Election Polls: A Review of the Disparate Methods and Results (Box 2)
      - Report to the Los Angeles County Election Commission (Box 2)
      - Tables Associated with the Prediction of the Outcome of the 1980 Election (Box 2)
      - Turnout (Box 2)
    - 1984
      - Background Polls (Box 2)
      - Black Voting/Registration (Box 2)
      - CBS/ New York Times Exit Polls (Box 2)
      - Early TV Calls (Box 2)
      - Election Projections (Box 2)
      - Iowa Democratic Caucus (Box 2)
      - Jewish Vote (Box 3)
      - New Hampshire Primary (Box 3)
      - Political Newspaper Clippings (Box 3)
      - Post ’84 Election Material (Box 3)
      - Primary Results (Box 3)
      - Projection Proposals (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - Election Survey of Non-Voters (2/5 folders) Election Survey of Non-Voters (3/5 folders) (Box 3)
      - Registration Up Three Percentage Points, Higher 1984 Voter Turnout Predicted (Box 3)
      - Turnout Up, Reversing 20 year downward trend (Box 3)
      - Voting Analysis (Box 3)
    - 1988
      - CBS Final News Study (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - CBS/ NYT Election Day Poll: DC/ OH/ NC/ IN/ TN/ NJ/ CA (Box 3)
      - Election Clippings (Box 3)
      - Iowa Democratic Caucus (Box 3)
      - Iowa Republican and Democratic Caucus (Box 3)
      - Jackson Percentage: 1988 vs. 1984 (Box 3)
      - National Election Day Poll as of 10/31 (Box 3)
      - NBC Political Coverage (Box 3)
      - New Hampshire Primary (Box 3)
      - Presidential Election Data 1972-1988 (Box 3)
      - Voter Registration (Box 3)
      - Voting Analysis (Box 3)
      - Voting and Registration in the Election of November 1988 (Box 3)
    - 1992
      - ABC News Election Night Projection Model (Box 3)
      - Blocked Nationals (Box 3)
      - Campaign Lessons (Box 3)
      - Election Articles (Box 3)
      - Election Night Transcripts (Box 3)
      - Evolving Use of Public Opinion Polls by NYT (Box 3)
      - Exit Evaluation (Box 3)
      - National General Election (Box 3)
      - New Hampshire Primary (Box 3)
      - Poll Results NBC News Decision (Box 3)
      - Post-Mortem (Box 3)
      - State Poll Methods (Box 3)
      - Various Polls (Box 3)
      - VNS (Box 3)
      - Voter Registration (Box 3)
      - Voter Research and Surveys Exit Polls (Box 3)
      - Voting and Registration in the Election of 1992 (Box 3)
      - VRS Exit Polls (Box 4)
    - 1996
      - America at the Polls (Box 4)
      - Election Polls (Box 4)
      - New Hampshire Primary (Box 4)
      - Plot of Estimates (Box 4)
      - Political Newspaper Articles (Box 4)
      - Primary Caucus (Box 4)
      - Review of 1996 Voter News Service Exit Polls from a Total Survey Error Perspective (Box 4)
      - VNS Cross-Tabs (Box 4)
      - VNS Primaries (Box 4)
      - VNS Questionnaire (Box 4)
    - 2000
      - Absentees (Box 4)
      - Black Stratum (Box 4)
      - Election Calls (Box 4)
      - Exit Poll Articles (Box 4)
      - Iowa Caucus (3 folders) (Box 4)
      - “Memos” (Box 4)
      - Mitofsky International Election Results (Box 4)
      - Poll Articles (Box 4)
      - Precinct Election Design (Box 4)
      - Respondent Selection (Box 4)
      - Statement of ABC News Concerning the 2000 Election Projections (Box 4)
      - VNS Computations & 2000 Screens (Box 4)
      - VNS General Election Exit Polls (Box 4)
      - VNS Submission to the Members (Box 4)
      - VNS vs. Certified Vote (Box 4)
    - 2004
      - AP Election Research (2 folders) (Box 4)
      - Associated Press Expanded Election Calendar (Box 4)
      - Delegates (Box 4)
      - Alaska Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - Arizona Delegate Selection & Affirmative Action Plan (Box 4)
      - Alabama Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - Arkansas Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - California Presidential Candidate Qualification Procedures (Box 4)
      - Colorado Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - Connecticut Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - Delaware Delegate Selection Plan – Draft (Box 4)
      - Florida Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - Georgia General Primary Election Qualifying Dates (Box 4)
      - Hawaii Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - Idaho Delegate Selection Plan – Draft (Box 4)
      - Illinois Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - Indiana Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - Iowa Delegate Selection & Affirmative Action Plan (Box 4)
      - Kansas Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - Maine Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - Maryland Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - Massachusetts Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - Michigan Delegate Selection Plan –Summary (Box 4)
      - Missouri Delegate Selection (Box 4)
      - Mississippi Delegate Selection & Affirmative Action Plan (Box 4)
      - Montana Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - Nebraska Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - New Hampshire Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - New Jersey Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - New Mexico Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - New York Delegate Selection Plan (Box 4)
      - North Carolina Delegate Selection Plan (Box 5)
      - North Dakota Delegate Selection Plan Ohio Delegate Selection Plan Oregon Delegate Selection Plan – Draft Pennsylvania Delegate Selection Plan Tennessee Delegate Selection &Affirmative Action Plan Texas Delegate Selection Plan Utah State Delegate Selection Plan Vermont Secretary of State Critical Dates Virginia Delegate Selection Plan Wisconsin Delegate Selection Plan Democratic Primaries – CT, CA, GA, MD, MA, NY, OH, RI, VT DNC Delegate Selection Rules DNC Labels DNC Party EMR – Precinct Numbers Exit Poll Estimates Exit Poll Laws Final Precinct Vote FVAP (Oversees Voting) General Election Official Results Top of the Ticket Races (3 folders) General Election Races General Election State Letters and Legal Information (3 folders) General Election Voter Analysis Handbook (2 folders) Interviewer Training Manual Iowa Iowa Caucus Michigan National Election Pool: Statistical Specifications for Estimating Election Outcomes NCPP Review of Election Polls NY Statistical Information Political Landscape Presidential Exit Poll Results Primary/Caucus Dates Primary Information RB Sampling Early Voter Reference Card RNC Party State Caucus State Election Material (2 folders) State Election Responsibilities State Fact Sheets State Fact Sheets (Complete) State Research Forms (Folder 1 of 2) (Box 5)
      - North Dakota Delegate Selection Plan (Box 5)
      - Ohio Delegate Selection Plan (Box 5)
      - Oregon Delegate Selection Plan – Draft (Box 5)
      - Pennsylvania Delegate Selection Plan (Box 5)
      - Tennessee Delegate Selection &Affirmative Action Plan (Box 5)
      - Texas Delegate Selection Plan (Box 5)
      - Utah State Delegate Selection Plan (Box 5)
      - Vermont Secretary of State Critical Dates (Box 5)
      - Virginia Delegate Selection Plan (Box 5)
      - Wisconsin Delegate Selection Plan (Box 5)
      - Democratic Primaries – CT, CA, GA, MD, MA, NY, OH, RI, VT (Box 5)
      - DNC Delegate Selection Rules (Box 5)
      - DNC Labels (Box 5)
      - DNC Party (Box 5)
      - EMR – Precinct Numbers (Box 5)
      - Exit Poll Estimates (Box 5)
      - Exit Poll Laws (Box 5)
      - Final Precinct Vote (Box 5)
      - FVAP (Oversees Voting) (Box 5)
      - General Election Official Results Top of the Ticket Races (3 folders) (Box 5)
      - General Election Races (Box 5)
      - General Election State Letters and Legal Information (3 folders) (Box 5)
      - General Election Voter Analysis Handbook (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - Interviewer Training Manual (Box 5)
      - Iowa (Box 5)
      - Iowa Caucus (Box 5)
      - Michigan (Box 5)
      - National Election Pool: Statistical Specifications for Estimating Election Outcomes (Box 5)
      - NCPP Review of Election Polls (Box 5)
      - NY Statistical Information (Box 5)
      - Political Landscape (Box 5)
      - Presidential Exit Poll Results (Box 5)
      - Primary/Caucus Dates (Box 5)
      - Primary Information (Box 5)
      - RB Sampling Early Voter (Box 5)
      - Reference Card (Box 5)
      - RNC Party (Box 5)
      - State Caucus (Box 5)
      - State Election Material (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - State Election Responsibilities (Box 5)
      - State Fact Sheets (Box 5)
      - State Fact Sheets (Complete) (Box 5)
      - State Research Forms (Folder 1 of 2) (Box 5)
      - State Research Forms (Folder 2 of 2) (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Alabama (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Alaska (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Arizona (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Arkansas (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – California (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Colorado (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Connecticut (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Delaware (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Washington, D.C. (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Florida (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Georgia (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Hawaii (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Idaho (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Illinois (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Indiana (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Iowa (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Kansas (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Kentucky (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Louisiana (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Maine (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Maryland (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Massachusetts (Box 6)
      - (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Minnesota (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Mississippi (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Missouri (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Montana (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Nebraska (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Nevada (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – New Hampshire (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – New Jersey (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – New Mexico (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – New York (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – North Carolina (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – North Dakota (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Ohio (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Oklahoma (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Oregon (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Pennsylvania (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Rhode Island (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – South Carolina (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – South Dakota (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Tennessee (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Texas (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Utah (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Vermont (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Virginia (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Washington (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – West Virginia (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Wisconsin (Box 6)
      - State Research Report – Wyoming (Box 6)
      - Voting Information (Box 6)
  - Subseries B: Midterm Elections
    - 1958
      - ABC Political Coverage (Box 6)
    - 1962
      - CBS News Reports (Box 6)
      - CBS Original Broadcast (2 Folders) (Box 6)
      - CBS Political Coverage (Box 6)
      - Election Articles (Box 6)
      - Missouri Voter Data Tables (Box 6)
      - NBC Political Coverage (Box 6)
      - Transcript of the CBS News Election Night Broadcast (Box 6)
    - 1966
      - Election Articles (Box 6)
      - Georgia’s Governor’s Race (Box 6)
      - Log of 1966 Election Coverage as Broadcast by WABC-TV (Box 6)
      - Maryland Governor Race (Box 6)
      - Taft/Gilligan Race on Ohio (Box 6)
      - VPA Construction (Box 6)
      - VPA Pre-Election Poll Analyses (Box 6)
      - VPA Post-mortem (Box 6)
      - VPA Results (Box 6)
    - 1970
      - CBS Election Results (Box 6)
      - CBS News “Election Preview” Transcript (Box 6)
      - CBS News Poll (Box 6)
      - CBS Political Analysis (Box 6)
      - CBS Political Coverage (Box 6)
      - NES Election Model (Box 6)
      - Voting and Registration in the Election of November 1970 (Box 6)
    - 1974
      - CBS Election 1974 Technical Memos part 1 & 2 (Box 6)
      - CBS Political Coverage (Box 6)
      - Voting and Registration in the Election of November of 1974 (Box 6)
    - 1978
      - How CBS Estimates the Winners on Election Night (Box 7)
      - CBS Political Coverage (Box 7)
      - Voting and Registration in the Election of November 1978 (Box 7)
    - 1982
      - CBS Campaign 1982 (Box 7)
      - Jewish Vote (Box 7)
      - National Election Results/Polls (Box 7)
      - Primaries (Box 7)
      - Voter Polls (Box 7)
      - Voting and Registration in the Election of November 1982 (Box 7)
    - 1986
      - Black Voting/Registration (Box 7)
      - CBS Exit Poll Detail (Box 7)
      - Evaluations (Box 7)
      - Exit Polling (Box 7)
      - Non-Response/Telephone Household ARF (Box 7)
      - Voting and Registration in the Election of November 1986 (Box 7)
    - 1990
      - California Primary (Box 7)
      - CBS Election System Algorithms (Box 7)
      - CBS News Election and Survey Unit (Box 7)